[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I thought I'll ask some questions about jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because we were speaking about it, in particular, with this, the word parimukhaṁ, and watching your mouth, which my mother used to tell me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Watch your mouth, boy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Funny, I knew what she meant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, I secluded from essential pleasures, secluded from unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_01]: It binds in the first jhāna, which is accompanied by thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if one does not appropriate one's mouth, that area
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what, you know, that's what you were saying the other day.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: How is that getting you to jhāna?
[SPEAKER_01]: How does that help?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think we discussed it a few days ago as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was basically the... the presence of the mouth as an organ, you can say.
[SPEAKER_00]: But basically, the presence of a mouth is a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: In your experience, in your general experience, or daily experience, the presence of that mouth, basically, it's a... it's an entry point for the mind towards the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's... it's a point of convergence, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in your experience as a whole, the experience that has this physical body present, and all the possibility of the physical action, verbal action, mental action, eh... the domain of the body and the domain of the mind,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the entry point, so to speak, I mean, the mind doesn't really enter the body, but in terms of the relationship, when the mind is directed towards the body, it's the phenomenon, it's the phenomenon of the mouth, that's that first point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you have
[SPEAKER_00]: If you have taken up your mouth, so to speak, if you assumed it to be yours, which implies all the possibilities based on that mouth, eye, speech, and anything that can be said, or any form of manipulation that can come out of that, if you have taken up the mouth, means you've taken up the whole domain of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: You say it's like a door.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a convergence point.
[SPEAKER_00]: I suppose you can say the doorway.
[SPEAKER_00]: You obviously need to be qualified, because it's not that you actually enter through that door.
[SPEAKER_00]: But yes, it's the first point of reference, so to speak, in the relationship between the mind and the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if
[SPEAKER_00]: You establish mindfulness in regard to the phenomenon of the mouth, in your experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, you're then guarded by that, or you're protected by anything that can come from the lower point, which is anything that's based on the bodily domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the mind hasn't appropriated the point of convergence, means anything else that converge on it won't affect you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's basically, yeah, like finding a gateway and then guarding that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the gateway towards the domain of the body is the phenomenon of the mouth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Verbal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Verbal involvement.
[SPEAKER_00]: Non-verbal involvement, possibility of verbal involvement, all of them are basically, by giving in to them or by appropriating them, you are kind of... your mind is sort of descending towards the body, towards the bodily actions, towards anything that pertains to the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if the mind is established in regard to the phenomenon of the mouth, say, in the first jhāna, then basically you are secluded from anything bodily.
[SPEAKER_00]: In a sense of anything that can arise on account of the five senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: In what way do you guard?
[SPEAKER_01]: How are you... how do you be mindful of the now?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to recognize it as a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no more straightforward way of describing it, because it's a... it's a... it's a peripheral negative.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the presence of the mouth is negative in regard to the act of speech, or any bodily act, or act of consumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to see it as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't actually have to go speaking in order to discern the verbal domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: On the contrary, you actually don't speak in order for that negative to be discerned, negative of the mouth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is basically, you can, just a different way of saying, the possibility of speech, the possibility of involvement, the possibility of verbal action.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of them come from that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, it's all rooted down in a physical fact that you have mouth present, right there in your face.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can be used.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, like, see, I mean, I'm uttering words, I'm saying things, I'm designating terms, but
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all material, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: My mouth, the sounds you hear as well, as vibrations, frequencies, whatever, they respond to your ear.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all on the level of body and matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, it's basically, I'm kind of painting up my thoughts to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm designating them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you just naturally, by not being mindful in regard to that, you naturally assume that your thoughts just kind of flow into these words.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there is no... there is no clear point... well...
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no point at all, when your thought suddenly changes into the word.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that which was a thought, enters the domain of the speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: There isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: There isn't a single thread that connects that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have a domain of thoughts, then you have the domain of speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have the domain of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they're completely independent of each other, and they can't mix, they can't connect, they can't interfere.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do you speak then?
[SPEAKER_00]: If there is nothing that comes from your thoughts, you speak by having thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, by breaking into the sound speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no smooth transition.
[SPEAKER_00]: Presence of thoughts has the possibility of it being simultaneously replicated, so to speak, in the domain of speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, the verbal action, the power of speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: How to purify your speech, you know, your wholesome speech?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, if you're obviously, if you're mindful first, first, if you're mindful of unwholesome speech, so you don't do it, you restrain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you don't necessarily see the purpose, you restrain from the unwholesome, unwholesome, saying unwholesome things, gossip, slander, malicious speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Greedy speech, anything like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You abstain from that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, by not cultivating these... by not maintaining these unwholesome habits, habits that are rooted in greed, aversion, delusion...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, by having your speech restrained, then you can start to discern the negative, that negative in regard to the act of speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the negative is just the presence of the mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, to me, it just seems important to, as you said, not to appropriate the mouth, because once you don't appropriate the mouth, then...
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it kind of solves a lot of the issues.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can, you can see, you can look at it basically, like, if you see this physical mouth that's kind of moving with the tongue and teeth and so on, if you see that as that matter because of which you're able to speak, the thoughts are able to be replicated in the domain of speech because of that physical mouth, by remaining mindful of the physical mouth, you won't be able to appropriate, you won't be confusing the two.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because why?
[SPEAKER_00]: You see its necessary cause, necessary determination, which is presence of the physical mouth.
[SPEAKER_00]: As negative as that mouth is, in your experience, when you engage in speech, it's still a real thing, and it is a physical mouth, presence of the physical mouth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without it, it would just be simply inconceivable to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: And obviously, you don't know how to speak immediately.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that just shows you the inherent separation between these domains, the verbal domain and the mental domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Baby can't speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Takes quite some time.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start making sound, then you start hearing the sounds that you yourself are making.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, obviously, you hear the sounds that others are making.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, basically, you start fabricating the connections between the thoughts, words and verbal expressions.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, obviously, the whole assumption grows in regard to it, where you just start assuming the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know.
[SPEAKER_00]: I speak what I think.
[SPEAKER_00]: What I think is what I speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it needs to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: That needs to happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to have that proliferation in order to be able to discern it and then not appropriate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in terms of the meditation, yeah, you can just be mindful of the presence of the mouth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing in particular.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't observe your tongue or whatever, roof, top of your mouth, or something on your lips.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just the fact that you have mouth present.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you can basically be mindful of, like, of the front of your face, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or the whole head, if you want, but basically the front, usually.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you're mindful of your mouth, and when that mouth speaks, when that mouth is making sounds, or the possibility that that mouth might be making sounds, well, you start putting like a buffer between you speaking, because you might want to speak, but it's your mouth that speaks.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't possibly speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you could speak, you wouldn't need mouth to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the speech is inseparable from the mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's difficult when you're not speaking, and you're mindful of the mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of easier.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when you start speaking, it's... You immediately lose the mindfulness, and that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: You train that mindfulness, or rather you refine it to the point
[SPEAKER_00]: That it ascends in the general background to such a level whereby even when you speak, that mindfulness doesn't get disturbed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by not having that mindfulness disturbed, there won't be any room for introducing the assumption of I am speaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: And mouth, as a physical organ, has lots of other, obviously, significance.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, as we spoke before, you know, it is a point of consumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: You consume things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, because the self, it's most closely, and probably, like, well, probably right off the bat, basically, as soon as you're born, baby starts identifying.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's sense of self, underlying tendencies towards the sense of self with the mouth.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what children... you're putting things in your mouth, everything, like objects, anything, because that is a way of assimilating them, of appropriating them, consuming them, or just of getting to know them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Chew it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Get it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feels like you are touching it with your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, obviously, that kind of grows further, and then you have various expressions that develop on top of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then the speech and all that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But basically, always, the food will always remain connected to the mouth, connected to eating.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even sensuality in general.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's... the mouth plays quite a big significance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it is a... it is a... it is a... almost like a symbol of assimilation, or rather stands for the assumption of assimilation and conception, or, simply said, appropriation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because when you eat the food, the food doesn't change in the sense of... it doesn't really become... it doesn't disappear from the world, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: It remains external.
[SPEAKER_00]: The food that was on the table, it's now mashed up in your stomach.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that stomach and the table, they're all part of the external world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, consuming the food is just having a revolve around these external things.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't actually get inside, in me.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't consume it, because I am not in the stomach.
[SPEAKER_00]: The stomach is external, same as mouth is external, same as the table is external.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the sense of self assumes the ownership, so it just feels as if it is on the other side, on the inside of the self, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why the food is always that kind of subtle maintenance of that assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: By eating unmindfully, you are basically maintaining the assumption of the self is consuming the food that's now disappearing behind it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's being taken.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it doesn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It stays in that external world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just goes through the mouth, contacts you with a taste, and then stays there, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stays in the external world.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can be moderate in your eating.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, you can choose, I'll have a little bit of this, a little bit of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you...
[SPEAKER_01]: But completely, it's a complete blur.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll have this, and then I'll ring a bell, and then I'll bow, and then I'll eat my
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll carry now and then I'll bow.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's just like a random observance, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: That means nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, you know, if you're pigging out and eating carelessly, well, there's no practice there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, either way, you can abstain from food entirely and still not develop any wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only way that you're supposed to eat the Buddha's chest is mindfully.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, well,
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindfulness, basically, already implies a degree of discernment and knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindfulness has nothing to do with the ritual you might observe before your meal, and during your meal, and after your meal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Be present with the taste.
[SPEAKER_00]: Be present with the taste.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I mean, if you want to do that, sure, but that might not necessarily lead you to anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the taste is present one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't... and that's the point that you need to recognize, which you don't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I must be present with these tastes, whereby you imply that if you're not present with the taste, what, the taste is gone, or the taste hasn't arisen, or the taste... No, the taste is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means you have no choice but to be present with the taste.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why making the extra effort on top of it, or being present with the taste, when you are present with the taste?
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is... that is, again, the taste, or rather the senses in themselves,
[SPEAKER_00]: Are also, in themselves, a point... well, it's basically a point where people get deceived.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, you... like in this particular example, when you... when a person thinks, or rather a person assumes, like, eating the food and the disappearance of the food through the mouth and chewing, stands for the assimilation of that food, stands for consumption, disappearance.
[SPEAKER_00]: The self took it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But basically, that food has just moved from one external point to another external point.
[SPEAKER_00]: From the table into the stomach, down the toilet drain, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Part of it staying in the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even that body, that table, that stomach, all of that remains external.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is absolutely no point from that external, from which this food can arise and get close to the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: What does get close to the sense of self is the taste, contacted by taste.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why that confusion sets.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same goes with the sight, with the ear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because your eyes are objects in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Objects you see in the world are objects in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the vision in itself, it's not quite, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: You see the world, but the vision in itself, that which you can't see, eh... hmm... where is that then?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you just assume that to be where yourself is, so to speak, because it's neither here nor there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by taking that up, then you create this division between the external, the sense objects, and the internal, me.
[SPEAKER_00]: By taking up the vision... Well, basically, you appropriate the sense bases.
[SPEAKER_00]: You end up appropriating your body by not having your mind developed in regard to the
[SPEAKER_00]: Contact.
[SPEAKER_00]: Contact by eyes, contact by sight, contact by taste, contact by sound.
[SPEAKER_00]: Vision.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or vision.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Taste.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you were to see that, be it an external object, be it an internal sense base, such as your tongue or your eye, eye organ,
[SPEAKER_00]: Would... like, okay, let's go back to the taste.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if there's no tongue, if there's no mouth, and if there is nothing to be consumed, eaten, put in the mouth, would a taste be possible to arise?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to... and like, not just that it wouldn't be impossible to arise, it would be also impossible to remain standing if these things disappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might have an arisen taste, but it's suddenly... well, it's suddenly you lose your sense of... sense of taste, you lose your tongue, you lose your head.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can this taste remain?
[SPEAKER_00]: It can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, no matter how closely tastes, or vision, or sounds pressure you, they also remain external, because they are rooted in external, and they can't break away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: But once you see that the internal sense plays as... As external.
[SPEAKER_01]: As external.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as the external object, as even more external.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you see the, the eye, or the internal senses as external, in the body, belonging to the body over there, then,
[SPEAKER_01]: That middle part, the vision, the sounds...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's... where... you said, where is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: But I think it's in between.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is in between, and it stays in between.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just, when you're appropriately in between, then... well, then you make it liable to being underlined, underlied.
[SPEAKER_00]: By the... by the tendency of the eye, the tendencies of the nose, the tendencies of the tongue.
[SPEAKER_01]: But as I just said, one said, eye is not appropriated.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't appropriate eye...
[SPEAKER_01]: If your mindfulness is properly...
[SPEAKER_00]: If your mindfulness is properly established in regard to the... the eye organs that are present in the world, is that because of which the sight is there in the first place?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: If that's established, then exactly, there is nothing underlining... underlying that whole picture.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because everything is now pushed externally, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: everything is now not taken to be mine, not taken to be pertaining to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's nothing underlying it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing underneath.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have to be... That you otherwise assume.
[SPEAKER_00]: You always assume.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, when you're eating, basically, your tongue, your sense of taste, your sense base of taste, that is assumed as underneath.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is assumed as mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the consumption of the food, the disappearance of the food, is disappearing under that niche.
[SPEAKER_01]: But isn't it enough?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, that's a further investigation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you think it's internal senses, then you're investigating the external form and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sense... sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you're investigating with vision and sound and taste.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, do you have to go that far?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I wasn't talking about investigation of it, because that already implies quite a lot of wrong views.
[SPEAKER_00]: People investigating end up explaining it to themselves, how these things work.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe just...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm not talking about investigation.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm talking about the direct discernment of the... and I think that's what you're aiming at as well, the direct discernment of the sense base as that which is already in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by being that which is already in the world like a sense organ, you can't really control it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have no say.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, your eyes are there working, quite an intricate organs, with all the nerves and optic nerves and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you have absolutely, absolutely no access to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you have no say.
[SPEAKER_00]: In it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if that thing fails, for whatever random reason, your sight is gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your whole world of vision, everything you've ever seen, everything you ever would see, everything you're seeing right now, everything that you ever felt on account of what you've seen, everything that you ever done, that you would do on account of what you've seen, is gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because none of that would be able to remain standing if these fleshy eye organs are not there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, recognize, oh, I can't possibly own this, even if I were to, you know, to make the extra effort to do so.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can say... and if you start seeing that, then you can even say, oh, these are my eyes, but it won't actually stand for the assumption of my mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's obvious.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just becomes obvious.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's not that you have to see it and then stop owning it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, seeing directly automatically results in disowning.
[SPEAKER_00]: Disowning everything else that... stands upon it, which is everything else, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I'm talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like in... Like, I don't have to look at the things that stand upon.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, of course not.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a complete mistake.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's basically the science, the worldly science, of looking at the things, or psychology, of explaining things and... That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...drawing parallel connections, etc.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing to do with... By staying mindful of that sense base, the body, that body there, properly, that's enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's enough for you, because you've heard enough, in terms of what you're supposed to see.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if somebody just comes to it, with all the wrong views that they still have, and then you say to them, just be mindful of that, it won't mean anything, and certainly won't result in anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, you can just be mindful of that, when you know how to regard it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as often they talk in the suttas, so, how should I regard the I?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, regard it as not mine, not me, not I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, yeah, yeah, be mindful of that, because that attitude is already implied,
[SPEAKER_00]: Through practice, through training, that attitude, you basically... you suffuse your mindfulness with that attitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can only do so when you know what the attitude is that needs to be developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: The attitude of disowning, disappropriation, dispassion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's not a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, this is not mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's already too coarse, that thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's already, it's already too, too coarse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if you're trying to, you know, to pull a, pull a thread through the, through the eye of the needle, well, if the thread's too big, it just won't fit.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to refine it, refine it until it can go through.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, sure, you can say attitude is a form of thought, but it's a much subtler way of thought than actual course thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because saying, yeah, it's not your... Yeah, it doesn't mean anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, watching that...
[SPEAKER_01]: Space.
[SPEAKER_01]: The space is a face.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your mouth, that space.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that can bring you closer to seeing your sense objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry, your sense bases, such as eyes, nose, ears, tongue, well, even face of touch, basically, the head is the foremost, you know, the head is your identity, the face.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, having mindfulness established to the fore of that face, in regard to that face, yeah, you're having a mindfulness established in regard to the sense bases.
[SPEAKER_01]: And being... and not appropriating, or should I say, being mindful of that
[SPEAKER_00]: The sense bases secludes me from... Well, secludes you from anything that is... that those sense bases are subjected to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That they are subjected to.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I hear a loud sound or see something intense sight.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, because of my
[SPEAKER_01]: Mindfulness has been developed strong enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'd see that that sight or sound pertains to the actual sense organ that is out there with that sight and sound, not out of you, because you stopped assuming that now.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not... you've stopped assuming the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see it where it is, out there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't... you can't be inside it, but you are not exactly anywhere, in particular, either.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, those visions, those tastes, can't go into you?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, because you is not rooted anymore to that which those visions and sounds pertain to.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, through the appropriation of the sense bases, or through being... through not having mindfulness developed to the extent necessary in regard to the sense bases, that which those sense bases are subjected to,
[SPEAKER_00]: You are subjected to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: These sounds enter you.
[SPEAKER_00]: This vision harasses you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It incites you.
[SPEAKER_00]: The taste arises in you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's all me in regard to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you become established in regard to this sense organs, as the organs, as external organs, which is the only way you can be established in regard to them,
[SPEAKER_00]: That internal dimension, that internal assumption of them, will fade.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because with the proper mindfulness established, it becomes apparent that the sights pertain to the eyes, the sounds pertain to the ears.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that keeps working the way they've always done.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you recognize there was never even room for your sense of self in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was just not knowing that there was no room, you assumed it there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why in the scene, there will only be the scene.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the herd, there'll only be the herd.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just carries on, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: For scene, there's scene.
[SPEAKER_00]: In herd, there's herd.
[SPEAKER_00]: In taste, there's taste.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there's... there's this, maybe, thought that you won't see anything anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, maybe.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's... that's not... not the case.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there anything further away from you all?
[SPEAKER_01]: In that convergence point?
[SPEAKER_01]: From your mouth, it's, you know, anything's further away, even down your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just a, just a bigger step away, even further away.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's exactly, yeah, the convergence of the mouth, the face, it's, it's basically the way the body is structured, you know, if your eyes were on top of your palms or something, if things wouldn't work the same way, but they're not.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of the major sense organs are based in your head.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus the head, thus the face.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're all based on the front of your face.
[SPEAKER_00]: And ears to the side, but still close to the front.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, if you're mindful of that physical presence, as that because of which the vision in itself
[SPEAKER_00]: The sounds, the sphere of sounds, the smells, tastes, touches, is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, basically, you cease to be liable to it, or rather, you're not being affected by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can anyone be mindful of that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not anyone can just be mindful of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no, because mindfulness, it's not just pure awareness, which such thing doesn't exist.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not pure awareness.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not aware of anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mindfulness, the right mindfulness, is basically inseparable from discernment, that can then lead to the proper knowledge of the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to... you can't just be mindful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of your face?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because that... yeah, be mindful of my face and then what?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to be mindful in the right way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to discern it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you can be mindful if your face doesn't mean anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you're mindful of your face, as that because of which the entire world that's right simultaneously present there, is standing right there,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you're mindful, basically, of the relationship between the two, of the determination and that which is being determined.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that determination, it's basically that face, presence of these sense organs, operating sense organs.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, see, there is a whole world that simultaneously stands upon that, including your sense of self, upon the presence of these sense organs, and you can't even
[SPEAKER_00]: On the level of your abstraction, you can't even conceive how it would be if you were to be in control of these seven sorghums, to control the workings, inner workings of the of the eye, of the lump of flesh that is your eye.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can observe it in the others, but they will never be your working eyes, because that's what you see with your working eye.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you can infer, that's my working eye.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if that inference, so to speak, does not stand as determination for the world that's simultaneously present as you're speaking it, as you're seeing it, then it will not be seen correctly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, eh... it looks the same, externally.
[SPEAKER_00]: The description that the Buddha gave of the senses, and the description that the modern medical science tells us.
[SPEAKER_00]: describes the eye as a flesh organ.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there is a big difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha described that and described it as a present phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the only way you can describe it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't possibly see your eye directly with your eye.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can infer its presence through other senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is the same thing the scientists would do just in regard to other people, senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the difference is, for Buddhist practice, that inference, when you when you infer your eye as the reason for your sight, you include simultaneously the present sight in that inference.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, the whole thing, the whole inference happens on the basis of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you start discerning the simultaneous principle of the determination and that which is being determined, that simultaneously standing upon it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Scientist doesn't do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: He can't do that because his assumptions of himself, of his world, are already far out external in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even when he looks at the other people's eyes, even if he says, my eyes are like the same, he... that doesn't pertain anywhere nearly to that which his eyes actually are in that experience, as that determination upon which the whole world of his stands.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by... by... again, be mindful of the... the sense bases.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then,
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, as I said, that is the closest you can see them.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the direct way of seeing them, as these third-party objects that are out there in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: But everybody can do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not everybody can basically see them as simultaneously as determinations of that which you're seeing, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can be thinking about your eyes,
[SPEAKER_00]: Or think about that just vision as a domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you see those, all of those thoughts, all of the thoughts that have resulted on account of it, all of the thoughts that will result in the future, on account of anything seen, that whole sphere, that whole domain, is right there and then, simultaneously determined by the still working presence of the fleshy eyes in your head, as you are thinking those very thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what no scientist can do, because if they were able to do that, they would basically fall back, or rather they would abandon the scientific view, which is the view of the external realities, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, if you see that simultaneously, and if you cultivate that simultaneous principle, then no matter what else simultaneously arises, no matter how inciting, how frightening the sight might be, it won't actually neither incite you, nor frighten you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the mindfulness remains unwavering, properly established in regard to the presence of the fleshly organs that are the simultaneous cause, determination, reason for the sight in the first place, whatever particularly that sight might be.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's funny enough to... it's not appropriate, you know... No, because what you're not appropriating then, is your thought of what you think the I is,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's then not being seen as simultaneously determined by the presence of the fleshy eye in your head.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if your mindfulness starts revolving around the presence of the fleshy eye in your head, that means your mindfulness becomes established upon that which is
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is going to be there for as long as you live, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is another way of just saying developing mindfulness of the body to the extent necessary for the final knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether it's eye, nose, ear, or basically sense basis, it's the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I'm so mindful of the whole body... Again, you can do that wrongly in the same sense you just described, that you can be wrongly mindful of your eyes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I'm mindful of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm observing the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that leaves the observer, or rather the assumption of the observer, out.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you don't observe the body, if you find the body is already there, because of which the entire actions that you're doing right now, aimed at this body, such as mindfulness of the body or whatever else, depend upon the presence of the body in the first place, then there is no room for that observer to step outside of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything is included.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because everything becomes undermined by your recognition that it all depends upon the external presence of this physical body, which I have no control over.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't want to be doing mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to develop to the point where mindfulness does you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where your central self becomes secondary in regard to the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's secluded from unwholesome thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's secluded from sensual pleasures, and it's secluded from unwholesome thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not appropriate on a sense basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's secluded from the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mind from the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is secluded, or separated, or detached from unwholesome thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, not detached, in a sense, but basically, the arising of unwholesome thoughts cannot be affecting you, cannot be appropriate, because you're mindful of the basis of their arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is in regard to the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you disown the body, even temporarily, so to speak, nothing that comes on account of the body, including thoughts, can't be yours, can't be affecting.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what's being recognized in the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a pleasure of seclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pleasure, basically, of... and confidence of, oh, you know, that you're safe here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing that arises on account of your experience as a whole can touch you.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is safe?
[SPEAKER_01]: Safe.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sense of safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because... Why does anything need to be safe?
[SPEAKER_00]: You can just have sense of safety in regard to these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't say, I'm...
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm safe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you can say, I'm safe, but they won't stand for the sense of I am, in terms of appropriating the sense basis, because through not appropriating the sense basis, you become safe.
[SPEAKER_00]: But sure, if you want to designate it, you have to say it like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no other way.
[SPEAKER_01]: The sense of safety is...
[SPEAKER_01]: I go inside, close the door.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm safe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you can extrapolate the nature of feeling safe and just take it up to the ultimate level, where you feel safe from your own senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you feel safe from the sights, you feel safe from thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean they still don't arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: They very much arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they can't take you with them wherever they go.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't move in regard to the movement of thinking and pondering, or in regard to the movement that that thinking and pondering is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is safety from, like, there is seclusion from those senses,
[SPEAKER_01]: One line of awesome thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's safety, there's joy from seclusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, to say it, I am... Well, as I said, you can say it like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, you know, as an experience, it's not... you don't feel that I am happy.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am happy.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't feel that I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't possibly feel that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because otherwise there wouldn't be a jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even any any quality that comes about from those
[SPEAKER_01]: From being in the jhāna, instead of developing mind, any quality that comes about is not appropriate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why jhāna is wholesome in itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why another jhāna is not an oblivious state.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a state fully founded upon unwavering mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is inappropriate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the mindfulness is established to a sufficient extent necessary, procreation becomes impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because appropriation is the result of mistake, misconception, unmindfulness, non-mindful attitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: Results in assumption, results in appropriation, results in maintenance of the ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Practicing the opposite undoes that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can only... the only person that can be mindful, right mind, is the person who doesn't appropriate the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, the person who knows what mindfulness is, has knowledge of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindfulness is not just a pure, indifferent state, technique, method that you engage in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can't do jhāna and then get to a state where you don't appropriate things anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't follow that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, practice jhāna, practice mindfulness of breathing... To enter the state of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, right.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: In order to enter the jhāna, you already need to disappropriate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: In order to... in order for mind to get settled in jhāna, the mindfulness needs to have been practiced.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, quite a lot.
[SPEAKER_00]: And develop such a wide basis of mindfulness,
[SPEAKER_00]: whereby it gets established regardless of what's happening around you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, on certain occasions, you can then just dwell on certain aspects of that establishment and enter the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: And certain aspects of the establishments is the aspect of seclusion, aspect of safety, aspect of confidence, aspect of thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's directing the mind to those aspects.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, someone tells you that those aspects are found in such a state.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: If your basis of mindfulness is developed to such a wide extent, that already contains all these things, and you already see them clearly, then all you need to do is hear what the first jhāna is, and by thinking about it, you enter it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is exactly what happened to Maha Moggallāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: When the Buddha told him, you should practice the first jhāna and study your mind in the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, he thought, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he went to the forest, sat under the tree, or on a rock, I can't remember, and said, first jhāna, first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is first jhāna?
[SPEAKER_00]: What did the Lord mean by saying first jhāna?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, he just recollected all the things that the Buddha said the first jhāna is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by recollecting them, he entered the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because his mindfulness was already developed to such an extent that he could discern these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Most people can't, because most people's mindfulness is not established.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it never will be, as long as their practice of meditation, in inverted commas, revolves around methods and techniques of observance, that somehow leads you into a state of, most often, oblivion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just like, for example, mindfulness of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says, here a bhikkhu gone to the forest or the root of a tree, or an empty hut, sits down, and then folded his legs crosswise, sets his body erect, and establishes mindfulness in front of him, or establishes mindfulness, parimal kāma, around his mouth or around his face.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what Pārimukha means, literally, around the mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Around the mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's already... he establishes mindfulness correctly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Say, even if you dispute that, if you say it doesn't mean around the mouth, it means to the front of the face, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by establishing your mind, your mindfulness, in regard to the front of the collection of your sense bases,
[SPEAKER_00]: In front of yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pretty much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, I'm discerning the reasons that underlie your sense of self, as an external given things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, oh, if I can't own the reasons of my sense of self, if I can't own and control that which determines my very sense of self, which is this sense, which says, I can't possibly have the sense of self as mine either.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what anatta is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not self.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not no self.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that which you've taken to be a self, it still stands there, but now it's seen as something that cannot be yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, it's not self anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Impossible to own.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the first section, it's necessary...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he establishes mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mindfulness in front of him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ever mindful, you breathe in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ever mindful, you breathe out.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by having that established mindfulness, properly in front of yourself, I'll just say this, in front of your faith, in front of your appropriation,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, let the body do its thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're noticing now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you got that established.
[SPEAKER_01]: But from a different direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: You notice now this.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's the breath.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you do mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's noticing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you can also notice, when you're anchored in that mindfulness, you can also then notice the sense of I am behind that breath.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now you're noticing it from that external anchor position in front.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that self is... is... is... is quite everywhere.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, quite everywhere, but now you are not there with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're with that mindfulness to the fore, mindfulness around the mouth, mindfulness in the front.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that becomes now your viewing point.
[SPEAKER_00]: There has no room for the self in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you see that... you see that body breathing, you see in-breath, out-breath, whatever, you see the act of breathing, and then you even see on top of the act of breathing, in the further distance, you see that sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: But seeing it from a different angle means, oh, this is just another phenomenon that arises in regard to things, as pretty much all the other phenomenons.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, it shares the nature of all the other phenomenons, which is, they are not self.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it becomes apparent that you had your sense of self, not because there was self, but because you had the attitude of regarding things as mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: People think I am, thus things are mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's actually the other way around.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because you regard things as mine, you generate the sense of I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: And seeing the self as not-self makes that which used to be taken as self now just remain a selfless individual.
[SPEAKER_00]: Individual in terms of still like a reflection of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: So to speak, the experience as a whole has its own, basically... Well, let's say, it has like a meeting point, which would be the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like the sign of the mind that we spoke before as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like a meeting point, which is where usually the... well, no, always, where the sense of self for Pūrṭhujana is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's where the sign of the mind is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, that's why it's rather easy to keep maintaining this, because most people don't even see that sign of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And seeing sign of the mind just means seeing mind as a phenomenon, however general.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, unless you start seeing the sign of the mind, you won't be able to establish mindfulness of any kind that's relevant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, for example, in satipaṭṭhāna sutta, mindful of the mind states, all that requires proper seeing of the sign of the mind, so you can discern it for what it is at the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's that very sign of the mind that is taken... it's because it just feels like a center of experience, it's taken to be that sense of self, that sense of I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if then you start developing, through the mindfulness properly established, pretty much like an external point of view, towards your own internal situation, then that sign of mind, in that sense of self, just become the extensions of the same principle of arising phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: In what I just said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if your mindfulness is established in front,
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, there is an active breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, while breathing, through that active breathing, you discern the sense of I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your mind doesn't go back to the sense of I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: It stays in the front.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now, it looks back and it sees that sense of I am still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, it's another indifferent, independent phenomenon that has arisen, same like all the other phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means it's not me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that special center that was always behind things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because now, look, I just see it as one of the things.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's out there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if these things disappear, it cannot remain standing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you want to look closer at that sense of I am, most often you find like a basically being underlined by the notions and concepts and images involving your own face, your own physical appearance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your own point of view of the appropriated eyes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here, inside.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now that here, inside, is seen as just external... another... external thing... external thing arisen upon external determinations.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, no matter how internal it is, it cannot be internally taken as mine anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you don't get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just stop regarding it as yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then it ceases to be your subjectivity.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just becomes your individuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you regard... you stop regarding it as yours, not by saying, this is not mine, because that becomes another part of your subjectivity, but by developing point of view that has no room for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that point of view is the view of... in front, around the mouth, around the face, around the head, or ahead of the sense bases.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mindfulness is much... yeah, well, to be mindful, you have to have a body.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you have to be alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, of course, but... but mindfulness being much larger, you know, larger in a sense, it covers all.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can cover all things.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can be in front of everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it can't be in front of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mindfulness?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, sorry, it can be in front, in the sense of the practice, but it can't go underneath the body, can't go underneath the matter, which is why it's possible to be mindful in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can't go underneath?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because the body is already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: The sense bases are already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can establish your mindfulness upon that, upon the physical presence of the sense organs, upon the physical presence of the body out there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that mindfulness can't step outside of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That would mean mindfulness stepping outside of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I know what you mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you say that mindfulness includes everything, that's... in that mindfulness, that includes everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Within that, you go further and you find the body already there, within that mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, sure, from the point of view of Putrajana's world, that mindfulness includes everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you don't stop there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You look at it further and then you see that that mindfulness is basically founded upon the presence of a physical body that you have no control over.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, you can't appropriate that mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Simply no room for any subjectivity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's good to keep drilling this, because on some days, all these things will make perfect sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything will feel like it's all in the place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, two, three days later, the doubt sets in, and then you just... it doesn't seem to fit with anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's exactly the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you keep drilling, until it falls in place,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then it falls out of place.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you keep trying until it falls in place.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it'll stop falling out of place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you widen the basis of your mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: You widen the basis of your discernment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now, the doubt cannot enter it from any angle.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when the doubt does enter it, instead of feeling like, oh my goodness, what did I do wrong?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You take that as basically having your work cut out for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, see?
[SPEAKER_00]: The doubt can enter it from this angle.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the angle I have to work now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, to remove the dove.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in terms of the jhānas again, but in particular with this, with sūta, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: It is with the...
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't do it from his point of view of the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't do it from his subjectivity.
[SPEAKER_00]: He does it from the externally established mindfulness to the fall, to the front.
[SPEAKER_00]: From that point, he pervades this body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Intentionally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even that intention won't be appropriated then, because his mind is established to the fore, around the mouth, around the converging point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when the mind is established around the converging point, looking back from the converging point, then it pervades and fuses and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything that's on the other side of the converging point, which is the entire bodily domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he senses self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's not there at the time, but that's where he senses self arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, it speaks of the bodily parts to gain your mindful of the converging point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, all of those bodily parts, all of them, I mean, as anything that could stand for basically the physical
[SPEAKER_00]: Physical aspect of your body, which is your body, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: All or any of those parts can serve as a converging point, if taken up readily.
[SPEAKER_00]: And saying, seen as a converging point, is nothing other than saying, seeing is that because of which your whole world is already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seeing it as a necessary condition to the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seeing it as a determination to your existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or for your entire life.
[SPEAKER_00]: And everything that comes with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Emotions, feelings, happiness, sadness, ideas, hopes, ambitions, everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Urine, feces.
[SPEAKER_00]: Urine, feces, nails, hair.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, so your whole life stands upon the presence of these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's... that's nothing to rejoice over, nothing to feel passionate about.
[SPEAKER_00]: On the contrary, it's something to recognize, oh, this will come to an abrupt end.
[SPEAKER_00]: Always.
[SPEAKER_00]: Death is always abrupt.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this will come to an abrupt end.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's actually quite displeasing, quite frightening, the fact that it depends upon these random external things that are composed in this body, random matter, random elements, they have absolutely no say over, no control over, can't even conceive it in the most
[SPEAKER_00]: In the wildest of abstractions, I can't conceive how it would be to control these elements.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, my whole life depends upon it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's... that's... any passion towards it, any desire towards it, any... any joy towards it, would disappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for somebody who is still very much inside of it, that seems very frightening.
[SPEAKER_00]: That would seem very frightening.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, my goodness, so what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Nibbāna is a joyless state.
[SPEAKER_00]: On the contrary,
[SPEAKER_00]: The joy... well, basically, say you have a joy on account of drinking a pleasant beverage that's full of poison, that you can't taste, smell, touch, see... nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't access that poison through any senses, but you know it's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's the most pleasant beverage.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the simile from the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you don't know the poison is there, you'd be enjoying that beverage, wouldn't you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's just pleasing in every possible aspect.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then somebody tells you, eh... there is poison in it, that will kill you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, would... by not drinking it then, you would give up the joy of drinking it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The joy of the pleasant taste, the joy of the pleasant consistency or whatever smell, the joy of the pleasant drink.
[SPEAKER_00]: You would give that up.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you would then replace it with a much greater joy of knowing that you are basically not going to be killed.
[SPEAKER_00]: By enjoying that poison.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, my goodness, I saved my own life.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, by abandoning the joys of worldly sensual life, the joys that arise on the basis of sense pleasures, you abandon all the dangers with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is... that can result in quite a non-worldly joy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Joy of freedom, joy of liberation.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the, the, the joy.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the joy.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, again, it says, when it's developed and cultivated mindfulness of the body, Māra cannot find opportunity and support within.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: As it's been the other days, that Māra is yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, very dear sense of self, that's where Māra is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you remove yourself from it,
[SPEAKER_00]: Mahārāja can't find any basis on it, any support in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He can't see it, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm sorry, in the suttas, mindfulness is the wakeful one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mindfulness is the wakeful one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's have a new take.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mindfulness sees you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindfulness is established upon the right order of things, order of the presence of the physical senses beforehand, simultaneously present with things that depend upon them.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the mindfulness you are not doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the mindfulness that includes you, as opposed to you performing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you find that mindfulness, you establish it upon that which is already there, the presence of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, not in that sense, I'm mindful of the body or I'm observing bodily sensations.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's putting you first, still.
[SPEAKER_00]: Keeping you in the center and then you're observing these things that are... No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to forget about your sense of self and establish your mindfulness upon these external things that needs to be seen as that because of which, well, you are able to even look at any external things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or internal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or internal and external things.
[SPEAKER_00]: It precedes them all.